
=== PAGE 14 ===
10
CONTEST IN H IG H ER  M ATHEM ATICS
the problem in question or its special role in the further development of the 
mathematical topic concerned. The final chapter of the book is devoted to M. 
Schw eitzers life work in the field o f mathematics.
During the preparation of this book, we have received valuable advice from 
Professors P. Erds, A. Rnyi, . Sz.-Nagy and P. Trn for which we now 
take the opportunity to express our sincere gratitude. Thanks are also due to 
Professor A. M oor and Dr. J. Szcs who read several solutions in galley- 
proofs and whose valuable remarks concerning their exposition helped us very 
much to present them in their definite forms.
It is our sincere wish that our book may arouse the interest of the reader con
cerned with the historical aspects of mathematics and that it may serve as a guide 
on the ways of young mathematicians both in our country and abroad.
The Editorial Board


=== PAGE 15 ===
C h a p t e r  1
PROBLEMS OF THE CONTESTS
The mark placed after the text of a problem refers to the chapter in which the 
solution is to be found. The letters in bold face denote the following main groups:
A : algebra
C: combinatorial analysis
F: theory of functions
G: geometry
N: theory of numbers
P : probability theory
R: theory of functions of real variables
S : 
sequences, series
St: set theory
Thus, for example, G.7 means that the problem is No. 7 in the Section  Ge
ometry".
1949
1. 
Let an infinite sequence of measurable sets be given on the interval (0, 1) 
the measures of which are ^ a > 0. Show that there exists a point of (0, 1) which 
belongs to infinitely many terms of the sequence. (R. 15)
* This is one of the problems treated in the book G. Plya-G. Szeg, Aufgaben und 
Lehrstze aus der Analysis II. (Berlin, 1925), No. 245.
(R. 1)
3. Let p be an odd prime number and  , . . ., ap and  b2, . .
bp two 
arbitrary permutations of the numbers 1,2,...,/?. Show that the least positive 
residues modulo p of the numbers ax bx, a<, b2, . . ., ap bp never form a permutation 
of the numbers 1 , 2 , . . .  p *
4. Let A and  be two disjoint sets in the interval (0, 1). Denoting by p the 
Lebesgue measure on the real line, let p(A) > 0 and p(B) > 0. Let further n be
a positive integer and 1 =  . Show that there exists a subinterval (c, d) of (0, 1)
n


=== PAGE 16 ===
1 2
C O N T E S T S  I N  H I G H E R  M A T H E M A T I C S
for which |i(yl  (c, d)) = fyi(A) and (  (c, df) = //((/?). Show, further, that
this is not true if '/. is not of the form 
. (R. 16)
n
5. Let /( x) be a polynomial of second degree the roots of which are con
tained in the interval [-1, 4-1 ] and let there be a point x0 [ 1, 4-1 ] such that
fixa) | = 1 .  Prove that for every a  [0, 1], there exists    [ 1, 4-1] such 
that )/'( ) I = a and that this statement is not true for a > 1. (R. 2)
6. Let n and  be positive integers, n S: k. Prove that the greatest common 
divisor of the numbers
is 1. (N. 1)
7. Find the complex numbers  for which the series
converges and find its sum. (F. 7)
8. The four sides of a skew quadrangle and the two segments joining the mid
points of the opposite sides are realized by rigid bars. The bars are linked by 
hinges. Prove that this apparatus is not rigid. (G. 6)
1950/1
1. Let {k}f=i be a sequence of real numbers having the properties  > 1 and 
kx 4- . . . 4- kn< 2k for n  1 , 2 , . . . .  Prove that there exists a number q > 1 such 
that k > q" for every positive integer n. (S. 1)
2. Consider three different planes and consider also one point on each of them. 
Give necessary and sufficient conditions for the existence of a quadric which 
passes through the given points and whose tangent-plane at each of these points 
is the respective given plane. (G. 14)
3. Let E be a system of if  4- 1 closed intervals of the real line. Show that E has 
either a subsystem consisting of n 4- 1 elements which are monotonically ordered 
with respect to inclusion or a subsystem consisting of n 4- 1 elements none of which 
contains any other element of the subsystem. (C. 6)
4. Find the polynomials fix) having the following properties:
(R. )


=== PAGE 17 ===
P R O B L E M S  O F  T H E  C O N T E S T S
13
5. Prove that for every positive integer  there exists a sequence of  consecutive 
positive integers none of which can be represented as the sum of two squares. 
(N. 11)
6. Prove the following identity for determinants:
is convergent and find its limit. (S. 15)
8. Let A = (aik) be an  -matrix with non-negative elements such that

Y_ aik = 1 for / = 1,. . 
n. Show that, for every eigenvalue X of A, either | X [ < 1
k = 1
or there exists a positive integer  such that Xk  1. (A. 2)
9. Find the sum of the series
10. Consider an arc of a planar curve such that the total curvature of 
the arc is less than n. Suppose, further, that the curvature and its derivative 
with respect to the arc length exist at every point of the arc and the latter nowhere 
equals zero. Let the osculating circles belonging to the endpoints of the arc and 
one of these endpoints be given. Determine the possible positions of the other end
point. (G. 21)
1950/H
1. Let a > 0, d > 0 and put
Give a closed form for /(x). (S. 17)
2. Show that there exists a positive constant c with the following property:
To every positive irrational a, there can be found infinitely many fractions   with
d
7. 
Let w be an arbitrary real number in (0, 1). For every positive integer k, let 
f k(x)be the number of points mx [,  + 1 ](m = 1,2,...). Show that the sequence


=== PAGE 18 ===
14
C O N T E S T S  I N  H I G H E R  M A T H E M A T I C S
(p, q) -  1 satisfying
and q = 1 (mod 4). (N. 2)
3. For any system xb x2,  . ., xn of positive real numbers, let
and
for v = 2, 3 , . . n . Show that for any s > 0, a positive integer /? < n0 (s) can be 
found such that for every n > n0 there exists a system x'v ' . . .,x' of positive 
real numbers with x{ + x2 4- . . . + x'n -  1 and / (xj, x2, . . . ,  x') ^ e for v =  1, 
2___ (S. 18)
4. Put
where p, q, r > 0 and p +  q 4- r =  1. Prove that
(A. 3)
5. Let 1 ^  ax < a2 < . . .  <  am ^ N be a sequence of integers such that the 
least common multiple of any two of its elements is not greater than N. Show 
that m ^  2[N/A r], where [^/iV] denotes the greatest integer : ^JN. (N. 3)
6. Consider an arc of a planar curve; let the radius of curvature at any point 
of the arc be a differentiable function of the arc length and its derivative be every
where different from zero; moreover, let the total curvature of the arc be less
71
than  . Let 
P.,, P3, Px,  and Pr< be any points on this arc, subject to the
only condition that the radius of curvature at Pk is greater than at Pj if j  < k. 
Prove that the radius of the circle passing through the points Px, P3 and Pr> is less 
than the radius of the circle through P2, Px and P(t. (G. 22)


=== PAGE 19 ===
P R O B L E M S  O F  T H E  C O N T E S T S
15
7. Examine the behaviour of the expression
as n  oo. (S. 19)
8. 
A coastal battery sights an enemy cruiser lying one kilometre off the coast 
and opens fire on it at the rate of one round per minute. After the first shot, 
the cruiser begins to move away at a speed of 60 kilometres an hour. Let the 
probability of a hit be 0.75a-2, where a denotes the distance (in kilometres) 
between the cruiser and the coast (a  St 1), and suppose that the battery goes on 
firing till the cruiser either sinks or disappears. Further, let the probability of the
cruiser sinking after n hits be 1  
(/; = 0, 1,. . .). Show that the probability
2 J l
of the cruiser escaping is - v   . (P. 1)
in
9. 
Find necessary and sufficient conditions for two conics that every tangent 
to one of them contains a real point of the other. (G. 15)
1951
1. Choose terms of the harmonic series so that the sum of the chosen terms 
be finite. Prove that the sequence of these terms is of density zero in the sequence
 1 
1 
1
1 > - > 
)    > 
>     (S. 2)
2 
3 
n
2. Denote by H  a set of sequences S =  {?,,},TU of real numbers having the 
following properties:
(i) 
If S = K}"=i  H , 
then 
S' = 
a  H :
(ii) If S =  KK=1 6 H 
and 
T = 
 t f , 
then
s + T =    + U = 1  H 
and 
ST = {s f}=1 6   ;
(iii) { - 1,  - 1 , .  . ., - 1 , .  . . }  # .
A real-valued function / ( S) defined on H is called a quasi-limit of S if it has 
the following properties:
If S =  {c, c ,. . ., c ,. . .} , 
then 
/ ( S) = c ;
If Si ^ 0 , then 
/ ( S) ^ 0;
/(S + T) = /(S ) + /(T ) ;
/(ST) = /(S )/(T );
/(S ')= /(S ).


=== PAGE 20 ===
1 6
C O N T E S T S  I N  H I G H E R  M A T H E M A T I C S
Prove that for every S ,  the quasi-limit/ ( S )  is an accumulation point of S .  (S. 3) 
3. Consider the iterated sequence
is convergent for every positive x  Denoting its sum by F(x), find lim F(x) and
.V+0
lim F(x). (S. 21)
5. In a lake there are several sorts of fish, in the following distribution: 18% 
catfish, 2% sturgeon and 80% other. Of a catch of 10 fishes, let x denote the num-
X
ber of the catfish and   that of the sturgeons. Find the expectation of- ------ .
I + T
(P. 2)
6. In lawn-tennis the player who scores at least four points, while his opponent 
scores at least two points less, wins a game. The player who wins at least six 
games, while his opponent wins at least two games less, wins a set. What minimum 
percentage of all points does the winner have to score in a set? (. 1)
7. Let f(x) be a polynomial with the following properties: (i) /(0) = 0;
(ii) 
^ X  
f ( a) 
js an ;n{eger for a n y  [WO different integers a and b. Is there a 
b  a
polynomial which has these properties, although not all of its coefficients are 
integers?
8. Given a positive integer n > 3, prove that the least common multiple of the 
products x1x2. . . x k (A 2; 1) whose factors xt are positive integers with 
, + X., + . . . + xk ^ /j, is less than !. (N. 4)
9. Let {otj, m.,,.. .} be a (finite or infinite) set of positive integers. Consider 
the system of congruences
(1) 
X = 2mj (mod 2m,-  1) 
( / = 1 , 2 , . . . ) .
Give a necessary and sufficient condition for the system (1) to be solvable. IN . 5)
w h e re /(x ) =  4x  4 x 2. D eterm ine the points x 0 o f [0,1] for which (1) converges 
and find the lim it o f (1). (S. 20)
4. Prove that the infinite series


=== PAGE 21 ===
P R O B L E M S  O F  T H E  C O N T E S T S
1 7
10. Let f{x) be a polynomial with integer coefficients and let p be a prime. 
Denote by zx, . . 
zp_r the (p -  l)th complex roots of unity. Prove that
/O l).  /(Zp-t) 
 f ( p -  1) (mod p ) . 
(A. 9)
11. Prove that for every pair n, r of positive integers there can be found a poly
nomial f{x) of degree n with integer coefficients, so that every polynomial g(x) of 
degree at most n, for which the coefficients of the polynomial /(.v) -  g(x) are 
integers whose absolute value is not greater than r, is irreducible over the field 
of rational numbers. (A. 6)
12. By number-theoretical functions, we wifi understand integer-valued func
tions defined on the set of all integers. Are there number-theoretical functions 
f 0(x), fi(x), 
. . . such that every number-theoretical function F(x) can be 
uniauelv represented in the form
an,  2, . . . being integers?
13. Of how many terms does the expansion of a determinant of order 2n con
sist if those and only those elements aik of the determinant are non-zero for which 
i   is divisible by n? (C. 3)
14. For which commutative finite groups is the product of all elements equal 
to the unit element? (A. 10)
15. Let the line
z =  X , 
  =  0
rotate at constant speed about the z-axis; let at the same time the point of inter
section of this line with the z-axis be displaced along the z-axis at constant 
speed.
(a) Determine that surface of rotation upon which the resulting helical surface 
can be developed (i.e., isometrically mapped).
(b) Find those lines of the surface of rotation into which the axis_ and the 
generators of the helical surface will be mapped by this development. (G. 23)
16. Let 
be a surface which is simply covered by two systems of geodesics 
such that any two lines belonging to different systems form angles of the same 
opening. Prove that 9r can be developed (that is, isometrically mapped) into 
the plane. (G. 24)
17. Let a be a projective plane and c a closed polygon on a. Prove that a will 
be decomposed into two regions by c if and only if there exists a straight line 
g in a which has an even number of points in common with c. (G. 16)
2


=== PAGE 22 ===
18
C O N T E S T S  I N  H I G H E R  M A T H E M A T I C S
Prove that for any pair of polynomials /(x), g(x)  A[x], /(x) | g(x) if and only 
if f(x) I g(x). (A. 22)
5. Let G be a non-commutative group. Consider all the one-to-one mappings 
a -* a' of G onto itself such that (ab) = b'a' (i.e. the anti-automorphisms of G). 
Prove that these mappings together with the automorphisms of G constitute 
a group which contains the group of the automorphisms of G as a direct factor. 
(A. 11)
6. Let 2/? distinct points on a circle be given. Arrange them into disjoint pairs 
in an arbitrary way and join the couples by chords. Determine the probability 
that no two of these n chords intersect. (All the possible arrangement into pairs 
are supposed to have the same probability.) (P. 3)
7. A point P is performing a random walk on the Z-axis. At the instant t =  0, 
P is at the point x0 (| x0 | ^ N, where x0 and N denote integers, N > 0). If at 
an instant t(t being a non-negative integer), P is at the point of x integer abscissa 
and ! x I < N, then by the instant t + 1 it reaches either the point x + 1 or the
point x  l,each with the probability  . If at the instanti, P is at the point
x = N [x = N], then by the instant t 4-1 it is certain to reach the point N  1
put
if, moreover, a is odd, then the upper bound 4 in (1) may be reduced to 2%J2. 
(N. 6)
4. Let  be a finite field of p elements, where p is a prime. For every poly
nomial
( 1)
1952
1. Find all convex polyhedra which have no diagonals (that is, for which every 
segment connecting two vertices lies on the boundary of the polyhedron). (G. 7)
2. Is it possible to find three conics in a plane such that any straight line in the 
plane intersects at least two of the conics and through any point of the plane pass 
tangents to at least two of them? (G. 17)
3. Prove: If a = p\xp\*. . .  p" is a perfect number, then


=== PAGE 23 ===
PROBLEMS OF TH E CONTESTS
19
[ N + 1]. Denote by Pk(t) the probability of P being at x =  k at the instant 
t(k is an integer). Find lim Pk (2t) and lim Pk(2r + 1) for every fixed k. (P. 4)
t  CO 
t   OO
8. For which values of z does the series
converge, provided that ck > 0 and
(F. 8)
9. 
Let C denote the set of functions f(x), integrable (according to either Rie- 
mann or Lebesgue) on (a, b), with 0 ^ f(x ) ^ 1. An element ()  C is said to 
be an extreme point of C if it cannot be expressed as the arithmetical mean 
of two different elements of C. Find the extreme points of C and the functions 
f(x)  C which can be obtained as weak limits of extreme points () of C. 
(The latter means that
is positive if n is odd and negative if n is even. (S. 23)
1953
2. 
Place 32 white and 32 black chessmen on the chessboard. Two chessmen of 
different colours will be said to form a related pair if they are placed either in 
the same row or in the same column. Determine the maximum and minimum 
number of related pairs (over all possible arrangements of the 64 chessmen con
sidered). (C. 2)
2 *
holds for every integrable function h(x).) (R. 3)
10. Let  be a positive integer. Prove that, for 0 < x <  ,
n + 1
1. Let av and b (v = 1, 2 , . . . ,  n) be real numbers such that
 j>  2:. . . 2; an > 0
and


=== PAGE 24 ===
2 0
C O N T E S T S  IN  H I G H E R  M A T H E M A T I C S
3. Denoting by E the class of trigonometric polynomials of the form
4. Show that every closed curve c of length less than 2n on the surface of the 
unit sphere lies entirely on the surface of some hemisphere of the unit sphere. 
(G. 8)
5. Show that any positive integer has at least as many positive divisors of the 
form 3 4- 1 as of the form 3  1. (N. 7)
6. Let Hn 0 )  be the wth Hermite polynomial. Find
for an arbitrary real y. (S. 5)
7. Consider four real numbers t b  U , t 3 , t 4 such that each is less than the sum 
of the others. Show that there exists a tetrahedron whose faces have areas
t3 and ?4, respectively. (G. 9)
8. Does there exist a Euclidean ring which is properly contained in the field 
V of real num bers, and whose quotient field is V? (A. 21)
9. Let w = f(z) be regular in | z f ^  1. For 0  '   L denote by cr the image 
by f{z) of the circle \ z \ = r. Show that if the maximal length of the chords of
is 1, then for every / such that 0 ^  r ^ 1, the maximal length of the chords 
of o, is not greater than r. (F. 1)
10. Consider a point performing a random walk on a planar triangular lattice 
and suppose that it moves away with equal probability from any lattice point 
along any one of the six lattice lines issuing from it. Prove that if the walk is 
continued indefinitely, then the point will return to its starting point with prob
ability 1. (P. 5)
1. 
Given a positive integer r > 1, prove that there exists an infinite num
ber of infinite geometrical series, with positive terms, having the sum 1 and satis
fying the following condition: for any positive real numbers S), S.2, . . ., Sr such 
that 
+ S2 + ... +  Sr =  1, any of these infinite geometrical series can be divided 
into r infinite series (not necessarily geometrical) having the sums 
S. , . . ., Sn 
respectively. (S. 6)
1954


=== PAGE 25 ===
P R O B L E M S  O F  T H E  C O N T E S T S
2 1
2. Show th at the series
is convergent for every positive integer N and any real numbers a and b. (S. 25)
3. Is there a real-valued function Af, defined on the space of the functions, con
tinuous on [0, 1], such that f(x) ^ g(x) and f(x)  g(x) imply A f < A gl Is this 
also true if the functions f(x) are required to be monotonically increasing (rather 
than continuous) on [0, 1]? (R. 4)
4. Find all functions of two variables defined over the entire plane that satisfy 
the relations f(x + ,  4- ) = f(x, ) 4-  and f(xv, yv) = /( x, y)v for any real 
numbers x, y, u, v. (R. 12)
5. Let ,, c2, 
be independent random variables of uniform distribu
tion in (0, 1). Show that the distribution of the random variable
tends to a limit distribution for n > oo. (P. 6)
6. Prove or disprove the following two propositions:
(i) If a and b are positive integers such that a < b, then in any set of b con
secutive integers there are two whose product is divisible by ab.
(ii) If a, b and c are positive integers such that a <  b < c, then in any set of 
c consecutive integers there are three whose product is divisible by abc. (N. 8)
7. Find the finite groups having only one proper maximal subgroup. (A. 12)
8. Prove the following generalization of the well-known Chinese remainder 
theorem: Let A be a ring with unit element and let Ax, A.,,. . 
An (n ^  2) be pair
wise relative prime ideals of R. Then, for arbitrary elements cx, c2,  . ., c of R, 
there exists an element x  R such that x  ck  Ak (k  1, 2 ,. .., ri). (A. 17)
9. Let p be a connected non-closed broken line without self-intersection in the 
plane S?. Prove that if v is a non-zero vector in 6? and p has a common point 
with the broken line p + v, then p has a common point with the broken line
p + av too, where a =  and n is a positive integer. Does a similar statement 
n
hold for other positive values of a? (p + v denotes the broken line obtained from 
p through displacement by the vector v.) (G. 1)
10. Given a triangle ABC, construct outwards over the sides AB, , CA 
similar isosceles triangles  BCAy and CABX. Prove that the straight lines 
AAX, BBX and CCX are concurrent. Is this statement true in elliptic and hyperbolic 
geometry, too? (G. 19)


=== PAGE 26 ===
22
CONTESTS IN  H IG H ER M ATHEM ATICS
1955
1. Let %, a.z,   > an and ^i> b.z, . . . , bm be n + m unit vectors in the /-dimen
sional Euclidean space Er (n, m :2 rj; let ax, a2, . . ., a as well as bb b.,.. .
bm 
be mutually orthogonal. For any vector x  En consider
n 
m
^ = 1 1  (x, a,) (a,, bk) bk
(=i *.=1
((a, b) denotes the scalar product of a and ft). Show that the sequence {Tkx}%L0, 
where Tx =  x and Tkx =  T(Tk~1x), is convergent and give a geometrical 
characterization of how the limit depends on x. (S. 14)
2. Let fx{x),. . 
be Lebesgue integrable functions on [0,1], with
i
j f(x )d x  =  0 (i =  1,. . 
n). Show that, for every a (0,1), there exists a subset E
0
of [0, 1] with measure a, such that \ f ( x ) d x  = 0. (R. 17)
E
3. Let the density function f(x) of the random variable  be an even function; 
let further f(x) be monotonically non-increasing for x > 0. Suppose that
D~ = j x~f(x) dx
 
exists. Prove that for every non-negative X
(p. 7)
4. Find all positive integers a,  (a > 1) and all prime numbers p. q, r which 
satisfy the equation p1 = q + r (a, , p, q, r need not necessarily be different). 
(N. 12)
5. Show that a ring R is commutative if for every x  R the element x2  x 
belongs to the centre of R. (A. 18)
6. For a prime factorisation of a positive integer N let us call the exponent of 
a prime p the integer  for which pk | N but pk+l X N; let, further, the power pk 
be called the contribution of p to N. Show that for any positive integer n and 
for any primes p and q the contribution of p to n! is greater than the contribution 
of q if and only if the exponent of p is greater than that of q*
1. Prove that for any odd prime number p, the polynomial
fl+i 
p + i
2(1 +jc 2 + (1 -  x) 2 )
is congruent mod p to the square of a polynomial with integer coefficients. (N. 21)
* This problem was proposed by P. E rds in the American Mathematical Monthly 53 
(1946), p . 594.


=== PAGE 27 ===
P R O B L E M S  O F  T H E  C O N T E S T S
23
8. Show that on any tetrahedron there can be found three acute dihedral angles 
such that the faces including these angles count among them all faces of the 
tetrahedron. (G. 10)
9. Show that to any elliptic paraboloid S ? x there may be found an elliptic 
paraboloid 3 ^ ., (other than 3 * ^  and an affinity   which m aps 3 e>1 onto S ? 2 and 
has the following property: If  P  is any point o f .S ^ such th at  (  )  +  P ,  then 
the straight line connecting P  and  (  )  is a com m on tangent of the two parabo
loids. (G. 18)
10. Show that if a convex polyhedron has vertices of regular distribution and 
congruent faces, then it is regular. (A system of points is said to be of regular 
distribution if every point of the system can be transformed into any other point 
by congruent transformations mapping the system onto itself.) (G. 11)
1956
1. 
Solve without use of determinants the following system of linear equa
tions:
(   =  0, 1, . . ., r  ) ,
where a is a fixed real number. (A. 7)
2. Find the minimum of max {| 1 + z |, | 1 +  z2 |} if z runs over all complex 
numbers. (F. 2)
3. A triangulation of a convex closed polygon is the division into triangles of 
this polygon by diagonals not intersecting in the interior of the polygon. Find 
the number of all triangulations of a convex -gon and also the number of those 
triangulations in which every triangle has at least one side in common with the 
given /-gon. (C. 4)
4. Denoting by a(n) the greatest prime factor of the positive integer n, show 
that
is convergent. (N. 13)
5. 
On a circle consider n points among which there acts a repulsive force 
inversely proportional to the square of their distance. Prove that the point system 
is in stable equilibrium if and only if the points form a regular /-gon; in other
words, considering the sum of the reciprocal distances of the I 
pairs of points
which can be chosen from among the n given points, this sum is minimal if and 
only if the points lie at the vertices of a regular /-gon. (G. 2)


=== PAGE 28 ===
24
CONTESTS IN H IG H ER  M ATHEM ATICS
6. Show that the number of the faces of a convex polyhedron is even if every 
face is centrally symmetric. (G. 12)
7. Let 
be a sequence of real numbers such that, with some positive
number C,
(S.7)
8. Let {/}=i be a sequence of positive numbers and suppose that   c?n is
iii1
divergent. Let further 0 <  e < -- 
 Show that there exists a sequence 
of
CO
positive numbers such that  b \ is convergent and
/7=1
for every positive integer N. (S. 8)
n
9. Show that if the trigonometric polynomial /(#) =  a   cos v d  monotoni-
rti
cally decreases over the closed interval [0, n ] , then the trigonometric polynomial
n
g() =   av sin v& is non-negative in the same interval. (S. 26)
>=i
10. In an urn there are balls of N different colours, n balls of each colour. 
Balls are drawn and not replaced until one of the colours turns up twice; denote 
by vy the number of the balls drawn and by MN n the expectation of the ran-
Vxr
dom variable vN
Find the limit distribution of the random variable 
 -
M
n ,
if N * oo and ii is a fixed number. (P. 8)
1957
1. Let Cjj (i , j  1,2,3) be the coefficients of a real non-involutive orthogonal
b
transformation. Prove that the function w = ^  cu Zj z) maps the surface of the
3
complex unit sphere   z{ zt = 1 onto a triangle of the vv-plane. (F. 3)
/=i


=== PAGE 29 ===
PROBLEMS OF TH E CONTESTS
25
2. 
For any pair U, V of points of a unit sphere dfc let UV denote the shorter 
arc of the great circle passing through U and V, provided that U and V are no 
antipodal points. Let Fx and F., be two points on 
such that Fx F.,< n and 
let g denote the set of all points P of dj satisfying the condition FXP + PF\  2a, 
where 2a is a constant less than n. Prove that if g passes through the vertices of
a spherical triangle Ax A2 A:i with A, A2 = A2A3 = Ai A1 = 
, then to each point
P] of g there exists a spherical triangle Px P-> P3 such that P2, P3 are also on g and
PyP> = P2P3 = P3P\ =  - 
 What is the connection between Fx F, and 2a in this
case? (G. 13)
3. 
Let d b e a  subset of -dimensional space containing at least one inner point 
and suppose that, for every point pair x,   A, the subset A contains the mid
point of the line segment between x and y. Show that A consists of a convex 
open set and of some of its boundary points. (St. 1)
4. 
Let FE(0 < e < 1) denote the class of non-negative piecewise continuous 
functions defined on [0, oo) which satisfy the following condition: f(x)f(y) ^ 
^ 
(x,  ; 0). Find the value of
5. Find the continuous solutions of the functional equation f(xyz) = f(x) + 
+ f(y) +  /(z) in the following two cases:
(a) X ,  y, z  are arbitrary non-zero real numbers;
(b) a < X, y, z < b (1 < a3 < b). (R. 13)
6. Let ) be an arbitrary function, differentiable infinitely many times. Then 
the nth derivative of f(ex) has the form
From the coefficients akn compose the sequence of polynomials
( = 0, 1,2, . . .)
and find a closed form for the function
(S. 22)
(R. 5)


=== PAGE 30 ===
2 6
C O N T E S T S  I N  H I G H E R  M A T H E M A T I C S
7. 
Prove that any real number x satisfying the inequalities 0 < x 
1 can be 
represented in the form
where {A-}f=iis a sequence of positive integers such that -*+1 assumes, for each
H
, one of the three values 2, 3 or 4. (N. 14)
8. Find all integers a > 1 for which the least (integer) solution n of the con
gruence a" =  l(mod p) differs from 6 (p is any prime number). (N. 9)
9. Find all pairs of linear polynomials f(x), c/(x) with integer coefficients for 
which there exist two polynomials n(x), i:(x) with integer coefficients such that 
f(x)u(x) + g(x)v(x) = 1. (A. 8)
10. An Abelian group G is said to have the property (A) if the torsion sub
group of G is a direct summand of G. Show that if G is an Abelian group such 
that nG has the property (A) for some positive integer n, then G itself has the 
property (A). (A. 13)
1958
1. Find the groups every generating system of which contains a basis. (A basis 
is a set of elements of the group such that the direct product of the cyclic groups 
generated by them is the group itself.) (A. 14)
2. Let A(x) denote the number of positive integers n not greater than x and
_ 
A(x)
having at least one prime divisor greater than ?/n. Prove that lim ----- - exists.
*-oo 
x
(N. 15)
3. 
Let n  be a positive integer having at least one prim e factor with exponent 
^  2. Show th at n  has as many factorizations into an odd num ber of factors as 
into an even num ber of factors. (Factorizations into the same factors arranged in 
different order are considered different.) (N. 10)
4. 
Let Px P2 P3 P,t P5 P(l be a convex hexagon. Denote by T its area and by 
t the area of the triangle Qx Q., Q3, where Q Q2 and Q3 are the midpoints of Px P4,
P> Ps, P3 
respectively. Prove that t < ~ T .  (G. 3)
5. Prove that neither the closed nor the open interval can be decomposed into 
finitely many mutually disjoint proper subsets which are all congruent by trans
lation. (St. 2)
6. Prove that if an ^  0 and


=== PAGE 31 ===
P R O B L E M S  O F  T H E  C O N T E S T S
27
ou
then Yj ak is convergent and its sum is less than 2eav (S. 9) 
i
7. Let 0 and ax be arbitrary real numbers, and let
( =  1, 2, . . . ) .
Show that the sequence
is convergent and find its limit. (S. 10)
8. Let the function f(x) be periodic with the period 1, non-negative, concave 
in the interval (0,1) and continuous at the point 0. Prove that f(nx)  nf(x) for 
every real x and positive integer n. (R. 6)
9. Show that if /(z) = 1  - axz + a.,z2 4- . . . for | z | ^ 1 and
where  is a positive integer, satisfies the following conditions:
(i) f(x)  0 if I x I ^   and f(x) 2; 0 elsewhere;
(ii) in every interval (/, / 4- 1) (/ =  k, k 4- 1, . .. .    1) the function /() 
is a polynomial of degree 2  1 at most. (R. 7)
11. 
Let a = (1)" (n = 1, 2,. .  
2N). Denote by AN (x) the number of the 
sequences 
1 ^ ix < i2 < . . .  < iN ^  2N 
such 
that 
aix + aL +  .  + aiN <
then f(z) has a root in the disc | z | :g 1. (F. 4)
10. Prove that the function
(N. 16)
1959
1. Let p be the /?th prime number. Prove that
(N. 17)


=== PAGE 32 ===
28
C O N T E S T S  I N  H I G H E R  M A T H E M A T I C S
2. Omit the vertices of a closed rectangle; the configuration obtained in such 
a way will be called a reduced rectangle. Prove that the set-union of any system 
of reduced rectangles with parallel sides is equal to the union of countably many 
elements of the system. (St. 3)
3. Let G be an arbitrary group, Hb . .. ,  H., some (not necessarily distinct) sub
groups of G and gu . . .,g n elements of G such that each element of G belongs 
at least to one of the right cosets 1 . . ., Hngn. Show that if, for any k, the 
set-union of the cosets {-, (i = 1, . . 
  1,  + 1,. . ., ri) differs from G, then 
every Hk (k  1, . . ., ri) is of finite index in G. (A. 15)
4. Consider n circles of radius 1 in the plane. Prove that at least one of the
2n
circles contains an arc of length greater than---- not intersected by any other
n
of these circles. (G. 4)
5. Denote by c the wth positive integer which can be represented in the form 
c =  k' (k, / =  2, 3, . . .). Prove that
6. Let T be a one-to-one mapping of the unit square E of the plane into itself. 
Suppose that T and T~1 are measure-preserving (i.e. if M  Cl E is a measurable 
set. then TM and T~lM  are also measurable and /t(A/) =  /.i(TM)= (~1), 
where  denotes the Lebesgue measure) and, furthermore, that if Tx N  for 
almost all points x of a measurable set N   E, then either N or E\N  is of 
measure 0.
Prove that, for any measurable set A   E with () > 0, the function n(x) 
defined by
(N. 18)
(R. 18)
is measurable and
7. 
Let {z}^=1 be a sequence of complex numbers tending to zero. Prove that 
there exists a sequence {e}=i (where e = -I-1 or  1) such that the series
8. 
An obiique lattice-cube is a lattice-cube of the three-dimensional funda
mental lattice no edge of which is perpendicular to any coordinate axis. Prove
is convergent. (F. 9)


=== PAGE 33 ===
P R O B L E M S  O F  T H E  C O N T E S T S
29
that for any integer h = 8  1 (  = 1, 2 ,. ..)  there exists an oblique lattice-cube 
with edges of length h. Propose a method for finding such a cube. (N. 20)
9. Let /(z) = z" 4 - i z"-1 +  . . . + a be a polynomial over the field of the 
complex numbers and let E f  denote the closed (not necessarily connected) domain 
of complex numbers z for which |/(z) | ; 1. Show that there exists a point 
z Ef  such that |/'( z 0) | ^ n. (F. 5)
10. Prove that if a graph with 2n 4- 1 vertices has at least 3 4- 1 edges, then 
the graph contains a circuit having an even number of edges. Prove further that 
this statement does not hold for 3n edges. (By a circuit, we mean a closed line 
which does not intersect itself.) (C. 5)
1960
1. Consider in the plane a set H of pairwise disjoint circles of radius 1 such 
that, for infinitely many positive integers , the circle k with centre at the origin 
and of radius n contains at least c2 elements of the set //. Prove that there exists 
a straight line which intersects infinitely many of the circles of H. Show further 
that if we require only that the circles kn contain o(ir) elements of H. the pro
position will be false. (G. 5)
2. Construct a sequence {}=1 of complex numbers such that, for every
/ 
0, th e  series
be divergent, but for almost all # in (0, 2n),
be convergent. (S. 11)
3. Let /(z) with /(0) = 1 be regular in the unit disk and let
Show that the area of the image of the unit disk by w =  /(z) (taken with multi
plicity) is not less than ---. (F. 6)
4. 
Let {//} be a system of sets of integershaving the property that for any 
*1 + 2, Hai n tfei is a finite set and kf7i 4= Ha . Prove that there exists a system 
{//J  of this kind whose cardinality is that of the continuum. Prove further 
that if none of the intersections of two sets 
contains more than 
elements, 
then the system {//} is countable ( is an arbitrary fixed integer). (St. 4)


=== PAGE 34 ===
30
C O N T E S T S  I N  H I G H E R  M A T H E M A T I C S
Show that there exists a function, continuous everywhere, which is nowhere 
differentiable in this general sense. (R. 8)
8. L et/be a bounded real function defined on the unit cube 
of the //-dimen
sional space and, for a given y, let Ay and By denote the parts of the interior 
of   on which / >   and f  < y, respectively. Show that /  is integrable in the 
Riemannian sense if and only if for every   almost all points of Ay and By are 
inner points. (R. 9)
9. Let  
A and  be ideals of an associative ring R such that  is con
tained in the set-union of the ideals At (i =  1,.. ., ri) but not contained in the 
union of any n  1 of the ideals A,. Show that, for some positive integer k, Bk 
is contained in the intersection of the ideals At. (A. 19)
10. A car is used by n drivers. Every morning the drivers choose by drawing 
that one of them who will drive the car that day. Let us define the random vari
able fi(n) as the least positive integer such that each driver drives at least one day 
during the first u(ri) days. Find the limit distribution of the random variable
00 
1 
.
Show that the sum of the series    is an irrational number. (N. 19)
A-1 
7. Define the generalized derivative at x0 of the function f(x) by
5. Define the sequence {c}=1 as follows:  = - -  , c,1+1 = c -  <? (n ^ 1). Prove 
that lim ncn = 1. (S. 12)
n-*- oo
6. Let /7/?Li be a strictly increasing sequence of positive integers such that
as n  o o .  (P. 9)
1961
1. Let  ( e, the unit element) be an element of finite order of a group G, 
and let /(^  2) beapositive integer. Show: if the complex A = {e, a, a2, . . ., a'-1} 
is not a group, then for every positive integer k(2 ^  - t) the complex
 = {e, ak, a2k, . . ., a('1),c} differs from A. (A. 16)


=== PAGE 35 ===
P R O B L E M S  O F  T H E  C O N T E S T S
31
2. Show that a ring R has a unit element if and only if any -module G can be 
written as a direct sum of RG and of the trivial submodule of G. (An -module 
is a linear space with R as its scalar domain. RG denotes the submodule generated 
by the elements of the form rg (r  R, g  G). The trivial submodule of G consists 
of the elements g of G for which rg =  0 holds for every r  R.) (A. 20)
3. Let /(x) =  x n 4- ] x"-1 +  . . .  4- an ( ^  1) be an irreducible polynomial
over the field K. Show that every non-zero matrix commuting with the matrix
is invertible. (A. 4)
4. Let /(x) be a real- or complex-valued integrable function on (0, 1) with 
\f(x) ! < 1. Set
(S is a matrix of order mn in the ordinary sense; E denotes the unit matrix of 
order n). Show that for any pair (m, n) of positive integers, S has only non-nega
tive real eigenvalues. (R. 19)
5. 
Determine the functions G defined on the set of all non-zero real numbers 
the values of which are regular matrices of order 2, and the functions f mapping 
the two-dimensional real vector space  2 into itself, such that for any vector 
 6 Eo and for any regular matrix X  of order 2, f(Xy) = G(det X)Xt(y) (det X 
denotes the determinant of X). (A. 5)
and construct the following matrices of order n:
where tpq =  cq_p. t*q = cp_q. Further, consider the following hyper-matrix of 
order irr.


=== PAGE 36 ===
3 2
C O N T E S T S  I N  H I G H E R  M A T H E M A T I C S
6. Consider a sequence 
such that, for any convergent subsequence
{ak} of K b  the sequence K *+i} also is convergent and has the same limit as 
{ank}. Prove that the sequence {a} is either convergent or has infinitely many 
accumulation points the set of which is dense in itself. Give an example for the 
second case. (A sequence xn -* oo or  oo is considered to be convergent, too.) 
(S. 13)
7. For the differential equation
Show that the set of the points x for which the terms of the sequence xn+1 =  f(x) 
(:,, =  jc; /7 = 0, 1,2,..  .) are not all different is everywhere dense in [0, 1]. (R. 10)
9. 
Spin a regular coin repeatedly until the heads and tails turned up both 
reach the number  (  1, 2,...); denote by vk the number of the necessary 
throws. Find the distribution of the random variable vk and the limit-distribution
of the random variable - _
as  > oo. (P. 10)
J  2k
10. 
Given a straight line g in the plane and a point  on g. Construct, with
out making use of the Parallel Axiom, the half-line perpendicular to g at the 
point  and lying in one of the half-planes defined by g, under the following 
restrictions: The construction must be effected by use of a ruler and of a length 
standard (i.e. an etalon-segment) only; moreover, all lines and points of the con
struction must lie in the chosen half-plane. (G. 20)
find all solutions of the form u(x, y) =  f(x) g(y). (R. 14)
8. L et/(x)bea convex function defined on the interval 0, |  wi th/ (0)=0
and f  -^-j= 1. Let further /() be differentiable in jo,  , 
and differentiable
at Oand - 
from the right and from the left, respectively. Finally, let / ' ( 0 ) >  1.
Extend fix) to [0, 1 ] in the following manner: let f(x) = / ( l   x) if jc  ( ,1 
.

